<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.7">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-06-08T13:53:32-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Bergland Lab</title><subtitle>Welcome to the Bergland Lab! We are an ecological- and evolutionary-genetics lab.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Farmers Market Outreach</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/06/05/Harrisonburg_Market/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Farmers Market Outreach" /><published>2021-06-05T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-06-05T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/06/05/Harrisonburg_Market</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/06/05/Harrisonburg_Market/">&lt;p&gt;The Bergland lab joined the Central Shenandoah Master Gardeners Association at the Harrisonburg Farmers Market to talk about insects, compost, and evolution. These outreach efforts are geared towards increasing public understanding of evolution an diversity and to promote the Backyard Evolution project.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The Bergland Lab promotes Backyard Evolution at the Harrisonburg Farmer's Market</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/Harrisonburg_interactive_2021.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/Harrisonburg_interactive_2021.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Backyard Evolution 2021</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/05/28/BackyardEvolution2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Backyard Evolution 2021" /><published>2021-05-28T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-05-28T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/05/28/BackyardEvolution2021</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/05/28/BackyardEvolution2021/">&lt;p&gt;The Bergland lab is recruiting volunteers for the 2021 Backyard Evolution Citizen Science project. This project aims to collect drosophilid flies form compost piles throughout the growing season. This work is in collaboration with Virginia Master Gardeners, Master Naturalists, the Piedmond-Virginia Community College, and the University of Virginia. This is the second year that we are recruiting volunteers after a successful year in 2020. For more information, please visit: https://www.bergland-lab.org/2020/07/11/backyard-evolution/&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The 2021 Backyard Evolution season begins!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/backyard_evolution_2021.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/backyard_evolution_2021.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Priscilla’s Paper Published in PLoS Genetics</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/16/priscilla-plos-paper/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Priscilla’s Paper Published in PLoS Genetics" /><published>2020-12-16T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-12-16T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/16/priscilla-plos-paper</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/16/priscilla-plos-paper/">&lt;p&gt;Postdoc Priscilla Erickson used &lt;em&gt;D. melanogaster&lt;/em&gt; hybrid swarms and a computational pipeline developed by former PhD student Cory Weller to understand how flies survive harsh winters in temperate latitudes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In North America, some flies can enter a hibernation-like state known as diapause, but the ability to do so is genetically variable. By sequencing nearly 3000 flies, they mapped which parts of the genome affect a fly’s ability to diapause. This trait is highly polygenic, controlled by hundreds of SNPs throughout the genome. Alleles that promote diapause are more common at higher latitudes where winters are harsher. In a field study in our experimental orchard at Morven Farm, flies kept in large field cages evolved increased ability to diapause in the late fall as conditions became cold. However, despite the seasonal evolution of diapause, the frequencies of SNPs contributing to diapause do not vary predictably across seasons in North American samples. Collectively, these results suggest that diapause-associated variants evolve differently across space and time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other members of the lab who contributed to the work include former undergraduate student Danny Song and PhD student Alyssa Bangerter. You can read more about the work at: &lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.plos.org/plosgenetics/article?id=10.1371/journal.pgen.1009110&quot;&gt;https://journals.plos.org/plosgenetics/article?id=10.1371/journal.pgen.1009110&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/priscilla_pub2020.png&quot; width=&quot;50%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Postdoc Priscilla Erickson used D. melanogaster hybrid swarms and a computational pipeline to understand how flies survive harsh winters in temperate latitudes.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/priscilla_pub2020.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/priscilla_pub2020.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Cory’s Paper Published in G3</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/16/cory-g3/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cory’s Paper Published in G3" /><published>2020-12-16T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-12-16T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/16/cory-g3</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/16/cory-g3/">&lt;p&gt;Former PhD student Cory Weller publishes work evaluating the feasibility and efficacy of association mapping in outbred population.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This work shows taht fully-phased genomes can be reconstructed from arbitrarily large multiparental mapping populations. This work also shows that association mapping in inbred panels could lead to high false positive rates and that this problem is ameliorated through a limited number of generations of outbreeding. We use this “Hybrid Swarm” approach to study the genetics of diapause in Erickson et al (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can read more about the work at: [https://academic.oup.com/g3journal/article/11/4/jkab062/6156828?login=true]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/priscilla_pub2020.png&quot; width=&quot;50%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Cory Weller, a former PhD student from the lab, publishes a paper describing the feasibility and power of outbread QTL mapping.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/cory_g3.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/cory_g3.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">PVCC Capstone Collections</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/09/01/PVCC-Capstone-Program/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="PVCC Capstone Collections" /><published>2020-09-01T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-09-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/09/01/PVCC-Capstone-Program</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/09/01/PVCC-Capstone-Program/">&lt;p&gt;The Bergland lab is collaborating with students and faculty at Piedmont Virginia Community College to conduct seasonal &lt;em&gt;Drosophila&lt;/em&gt; collections at Carter Mountain Orchard in Charlottesville. Students in the Science 299 class will be studying species abundance, behavior, and other aspects of fly biology as independent research projects while contributing to the Bergland lab’s ongoing seasonal field collections. More information about PVCC’s capstone research program is available here: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ableweb.org/biologylabs/wp-content/uploads/volumes/vol-39/Vondrasek.pdf&quot;&gt;https://www.ableweb.org/biologylabs/wp-content/uploads/volumes/vol-39/Vondrasek.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">We are collaborating with Piedmont Virginia Community College to conduct seasonal Drosophila collections at Carter Mountain Orchard.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/PVCC-20200901.JPG" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/PVCC-20200901.JPG" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Backyard Evolution</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/07/11/backyard-evolution/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Backyard Evolution" /><published>2020-07-11T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-07-11T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/07/11/backyard-evolution</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/07/11/backyard-evolution/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;top&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/BackyardEvolution/bkydevo1.png&quot; style=&quot;float:right&quot; width=&quot;30%&quot; height=&quot;30%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;evolution-in-your-backyard&quot;&gt;Evolution in your backyard&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For many plants, animals, and fungi, we think of the seasons as a cycle of growth and dormancy. What is growth? For an individual, growth is the transition from one stage of life to another; the accumulation of resources. However, for a population, growth is the increase in population size across time. Many of the organisms in your backyard - for instance small invertebrates and weedy plants - have rapid development time, and are able to undergo multiple generations between spring to fall. The environment changes during the course of the growing season, imposing variable natural selection through time. As these populations grow, and eventually decline, they evolve in response to these changing environments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dna-as-a-historical-record&quot;&gt;DNA as a historical record&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can observe evolutionary change in populations through the analysis of DNA. Because most individuals in a population have slightly different genomes, we can infer the evolutionary history of the population and species. In some cases, such patterns reveal the more distant past, for instance large scale migration events. In other cases, we identify regions of the genome that have recently undergone adaptive evolution. Patterns of variation not only tell the story of the past, but also the present. We can track evolutionary dynamics in real-time. And, we can do it from your backyard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fruit-flies-and-compost-piles&quot;&gt;Fruit flies and compost piles&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your compost pile is teaming with life, and fruit flies are an important part of that ecosystem. Fruit flies typically eat bacteria and fungi that decompose your scraps, and are therefore part of the decomposition cycles that make the world go around. Over the course of the summer, your pile will likely be inhabited by about a dozen species of fruit flies, in addition to many other flying, walking, and crawling invertebrates. For some species of fruit flies, 10-15 generations can pass between the spring and fall. Populations of fruit flies evolve over the course of the growing season as aspects of the nutritional and thermal environment change. By sampling fruit flies from your compost pile over the growing season, we can track the evolutionary dynamics of fruit flies in real-time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;sign-up&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;will-you-commit-to-sampling-and-preserving-small-flying-insects-from-your-compost-piles-2x-per-month-july---december&quot;&gt;Will you commit to sampling and preserving small flying insects from your compost piles 2x per month July - December?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&quot;if-you-miss-a-week-or-two-thats-okay&quot;&gt;*If you miss a week or two, that’s okay!&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;participate-in-a-world-wide-effort&quot;&gt;Participate in a world-wide effort&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your participation in this project will contribute to an ongoing, international collaboration of fruit fly biologists to study the genomes of flies sampled throughout the world. Your samples will represent a unique contribution from Virginia. Read more about this effort at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.droseu.net&quot;&gt;https://www.droseu.net&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;to-sign-up-click-here&quot;&gt;To sign up, click &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSdI_mAGyaLcagkICDY0XUnVwyIv2kuT15rcAjIrePtSQNQhmg/viewform?embedded=true&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;we-supply-everything-you-need-to-participate&quot;&gt;We supply everything you need to participate!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;columns is-multiline&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;column is-3&quot;&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;The Kit&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Drosophila net&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Collection vials&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Preservation tubes&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;75% Ethanol&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Eye dropper&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Specimen labels&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;A funnel&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Collection Log&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Collection Manual&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;column is-3&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/BackyardEvolution/bkydevo2.png&quot; width=&quot;258&quot; height=&quot;300px&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;column is-3&quot;&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here is an example of a filled collection vial. Flies were collected by gently kicking a compost pile. There are &lt;strong&gt;~50 flies in there, so multiple vials might be necessary to get the requested ~200 flies.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;column is-2&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/BackyardEvolution/bkydevo3.png&quot; width=&quot;150px&quot; height=&quot;228px&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;how-to&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;learn-how-to-collect-flies-with-this-video&quot;&gt;Learn how to collect flies with this video:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;iframe title=&quot;vimeo-player&quot; src=&quot;https://player.vimeo.com/video/429830849&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;360&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;heres-what-youll-be-doing-2x-a-month&quot;&gt;Here’s what you’ll be doing 2x a month:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Goal&lt;/strong&gt;: We want you to sample ~100-200 fruit-flies every several weeks over the growing season and into early winter.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fruit flies are most active in the early morning (6:00AM-9:00AM) or evening (6:00PM-9:00PM), and will be easier to collect then. They may be hiding in the heat of the day.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;To sample&lt;/strong&gt;, first hold a large collection vial in your non-dominant hand; keep the lid nearby. Then, with your other hand, sweep your net back and forth in a gentle motion and kick or tap your compost pile with your foot.
Many small flying things will emerge. Capture as many as you can in your net. Keep sweeping the net back and forth to keep the flies in the tip of your net. Then, in a swift motion, place your collection vial in the net tip and tap the flies into the vial. Using a tapping motion, tap the flies to the bottom of the vial and cover the vial with two or three fingers, tapping the flies down on your knee. Then, take the lid and screw it onto the vial. It might take a couple of tries. If the flies escape, give them a minute to settle down on the pile and then try again. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your sample likely contains anywhere from 10-100 flies and multiple species. Take a look at your vial. How many unique species do you think there are? Write down your estimate on your sample label.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;To preserve&lt;/strong&gt; your flies for genetic analysis, you will be storing them in 75% ethanol. First, take a preservation tube and fill it ~1/3 full with 75% ethanol using your plastic eye-dropper. Place your funnel in the opening to the preservation tube and seat both upright, using your specimen box. Using a tapping motion, tap your vial
down to knock the flies to the bottom of the collection tube. Unscrew the vial and place two or three fingers over the top. In a swift motion, invert the collection vial into the funnel and tap* the flies down, into the ethanol.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ideally, you will fill the preservation tube more than half way full with flies. You might need to take multiple samples from your pile on a collection day to get that many. If, after two or three nettings, you cannot get the vial half full, then stop. Once your collection is complete, firmly press the cap down (it’ll snap closed) and place vial upright in the freezer. This ensures that DNA will be preserved in a high quality state.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Record&lt;/strong&gt; your sample by filling in the date and time of collection on your specimen label and apply to the vial. Please use a pencil or ball-point pen, as Sharpies tend to bleed when exposed to ethanol. Your labels will contain a unique collector ID (that’s you!) and a sample number. For safety, record the sample number, time, and
date on your collection log.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will &lt;strong&gt;pick-up&lt;/strong&gt; your samples at the end of the year (&lt;strong&gt;December 1-15 2020, or earlier upon request&lt;/strong&gt;). &lt;br /&gt;
We will &lt;strong&gt;remind&lt;/strong&gt; you to collect every two weeks via text message or email (your choice).&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*&lt;strong&gt;Cold shock your flies.&lt;/strong&gt; If you are having a difficult time transferring your flies from the collection vial to the preservation tube, place the collection vial in the freezer for ~1-2 minutes. This will slow the flies down.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What species of fruit flies can you expect to find?&lt;/strong&gt; In Central Virginia, we typically find about 10 species of flies. Some of these species are endemic to Virginia and North America. One group of endemic species that you can easily spot are species in the &lt;em&gt;affinis&lt;/em&gt; group. They tend to be quite dark and males have bright red testicles that are visible on the bottom of their abdomen. Other species you find are invasive, and have established in North America over the last several hundred
years. One of these species is the genetic model species, &lt;em&gt;Drosophila melanogaster&lt;/em&gt;. Even though this species is not native, it is capable of overwintering and populations in your backyard might be permanent. Most of the species you collect are not economically important pests. One exception is &lt;em&gt;Drosophila suzukii&lt;/em&gt;, the spotted wing Drosophila. This species has colonized the world in the last decade and is a major pest on soft-skinned fruits. An excellent resource for species identification
and natural history of many of the species in our area can be found in &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Drosophilids of the Midwest and Northeast (2018) by Werner, Steenwinkel, and Jaenike&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://digitalcommons.mtu.edu/oabooks/1/&quot;&gt;https://digitalcommons.mtu.edu/oabooks/1/&lt;/a&gt; (the 2nd version includes bedtime stories for kids!)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What are we going to do with the flies you collect?&lt;/strong&gt; Samples that you collect during this first year will be sorted by students at UVA. We will then sequence the genomes of one species you collect, &lt;em&gt;D. melanogaster&lt;/em&gt;, using a technique called Illumina sequencing. This approach will allow us
to track the frequency of every genetic variant in the genome through the growing season. This is the basic approach that we use to study the evolutionary process. The remaining samples of species will be retained for future work.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2020 Backyard Evolution collection effort is a pilot project that will augment ongoing research in the Bergland lab. We aim to include ~35 participants this year, and will be pursuing National Science Foundation funding to expand the program to include more of the state for 2021-2026. We look forward to working with you to incorporate your ideas to improve this project and to increase outreach and education efforts.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;diversity&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Statement on the evolution of diversity.&lt;/strong&gt; In many species, populations differ from each other and these different varieties are sometimes locally adapted to the environment where they are found. It is easy to relate this ubiquitous biological phenomenon to racial categories. We cannot confuse ancestry and evolutionary history with race. Racial labels reflect the imposition of power of one group over another and arbitrary distinctions of who is superior and inferior. There is no biological justification for oppression. There is no better and worse, just different.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;covid&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;COVID-19 safety&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Collection kits will be dropped off at your house with no personal contact.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a id=&quot;privacy&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Privacy statement&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will only use your contact information to remind you to collect. For research purposes, we will use latitude and longitude associated with your house along with the answers to your survey questions. Your name will not be linked to your address for any publication and your house location will be only presented as latitude and longitude (within ~1/2 mile of actual address).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;contact&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;any-questions&quot;&gt;ANY QUESTIONS?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Email &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:virginia.backyard.flies@gmail.com&quot;&gt;virginia.backyard.flies@gmail.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;to-sign-up-visit-this-link&quot;&gt;TO SIGN UP, VISIT &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSdI_mAGyaLcagkICDY0XUnVwyIv2kuT15rcAjIrePtSQNQhmg/viewform?embedded=true&quot;&gt;THIS LINK&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;drosopholids-of-the-midwest-and-northeast&quot;&gt;Drosopholids of the Midwest and Northeast&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check out this excellent guide to drosophilid flies by Thomas Werner, Tessa Steenwinkel, and John Jaenike
&lt;a href=&quot;https://digitalcommons.mtu.edu/oabooks/1/&quot; download=&quot;&quot;&gt; here &lt;/a&gt;. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/BackyardEvolution/DrosopholidsGuide.jpg&quot; width=&quot;65%&quot; height=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Participate in a citizen science project! The Bergland Lab at UVA is looking for volunteers to collect and preserve flying insects from their compost piles this spring, summer, and fall. Click below to read more!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/BackyardEvolution/backyardEvoHeader.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/BackyardEvolution/backyardEvoHeader.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Monday, February 4, 2018</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/02/04/February-4-2018/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Monday, February 4, 2018" /><published>2018-02-04T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-02-04T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2018/02/04/February-4-2018</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2018/02/04/February-4-2018/">&lt;h1 id=&quot;monday-february-4-2018&quot;&gt;Monday, February 4, 2018&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dörthe Becker, a postdoc in the Bergland lab, was recently awarded a Horizon 2020 Marie Skłodowska-Curie fellowship funded by the European Commission. The fellowship will support her research examining how local adaptation affects sex and dormancy strategies in the ecological and genomic model organism Daphnia. Specifically, Dörthe will investigate the molecular mechanisms that drive sex specialization, and assess how environmental heterogeneity is contributing to genetic variation within and across natural populations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Dörthe Becker, a postdoc in the Bergland lab, was recently awarded a Horizon 2020 Marie Skłodowska-Curie fellowship funded by the European Commission.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/daphniaDorset.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/daphniaDorset.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Friday, Jan 18, 2018</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/01/18/January-18-2018/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Friday, Jan 18, 2018" /><published>2018-01-18T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-01-18T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2018/01/18/January-18-2018</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2018/01/18/January-18-2018/">&lt;h1 id=&quot;friday-jan-18-2018&quot;&gt;Friday, Jan 18, 2018&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Karen Barnard-Kubow, a postdoc in the Bergland Lab, was recently awarded a NIH NRSA postdoctoral fellowship. The fellowship will support her research examining how mixed reproductive strategies may act as a mechanism of balancing selection in cyclic parthenogens, and assessing the impact of this balancing selection on patterns of genetic diversity genome-wide.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Karen Barnard-Kubow, a postdoc in the Bergland Lab, was recently awarded a NIH NRSA postdoctoral fellowship.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/daphniaDorset.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/daphniaDorset.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Monday, Dec 18, 2017</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/12/18/December-18-2017/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Monday, Dec 18, 2017" /><published>2017-12-18T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-12-18T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2017/12/18/December-18-2017</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2017/12/18/December-18-2017/">&lt;h1 id=&quot;monday-dec-18-2017&quot;&gt;Monday, Dec 18, 2017&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alan co-authors a paper in eLife with members of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://sites.krieger.jhu.edu/johnstonlab/&quot;&gt;Johnston lab at Johns Hopkins&lt;/a&gt;. This paper identifies a common insertion polymorphism that affects color preference in flies. Read more &lt;a href=&quot;https://elifesciences.org/articles/29593&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Alan co-authors a paper in eLife with members of the Johnston lab at Johns Hopkins.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/daphniaDorset.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/daphniaDorset.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Tuesday, Oct 31, 2017</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/10/31/October-31-2017/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tuesday, Oct 31, 2017" /><published>2017-10-31T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-10-31T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2017/10/31/October-31-2017</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2017/10/31/October-31-2017/">&lt;h1 id=&quot;tuesday-oct-31-2017&quot;&gt;Tuesday, Oct 31, 2017&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alan publishes a paper in PNAS. Using simulations and theory, this paper demonstrates the necessary conditions for stable oscillations in allele frequency over seasonal time scales. Read more &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pnas.org/content/early/2017/10/27/1702994114.abstract.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Alan publishes a paper in PNAS.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/daphniaDorset.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/daphniaDorset.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>